Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998) (partial transcript included in two folders), 1990-1991
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Hazard case. How defendants were caught. Kept in touch with defendants for many years.History of anti-Semitism in Russia, Russian Revolution, MarxismVolunteered to go to Russia with Percy Sutton to assess the civil rights situation in 1972-73. [10:00 - 20:00] More on experiences in Russia. Being followed by the KGB. Visit to the home of an unemployed professor, where only his 14-year-old son spoke any English. Using a toy to communicate with the family. [20:00 - end] Had to go to Kiev to get the facts of a case in which a man named Feldman had applied for a visa to Israel or the United States. He was charged with hooliganism (similar to disorderly conduct) after making a woman drop a cake she was carrying by accidentally bumping into her.O'Dwyer had found a written record of the case so that they could bring it to light as an example of a violation of civil rights.Attempt to go to Kiev. Description of airport and plane not leaving. Going to see movie in Moscow. (Cd 2, Track 2)
    [12:57] Did you meet any Jewish people in Russia at that time who were accomplished and educated?
    [15:44] What did you feel at that time?
    [16:08] Whose home was this?
    [16:22] Do you remember what school he was working at?
    [18:10] This is with the young boy? So that nothing could be reported or retained? You had to keep everything in your minds?
    [18:27] It was just a toy here - my children have those.
    [18:38] Had you brought that with you or was that supplied to you in Russia?
    [18:55] Is it possible that that was used as a tool in school for the children similar to the old fashioned slate? And also save paper?
    [20:36] Did they actually call it hooliganism?
    [21:45] Who told you this? Did Mr. Feldman? You never met him?
    [21:58] You never met him because he had this brush with this woman and…?
    [22:41] What was his profession? Do you recall?
    [23:29] Was it from that record that you found out what happened to him or were you told by his relatives as well?
    [28:59] So your friend had no way of knowing exactly why you weren't going to Kiev but just that word came back, "There's no plane going to Kiev."
    [29:42] The one and only cinema in Moscow?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 October 1990, Oct 17, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Russia c. 1972 - O'Dwyer in Moscow gathering whatever information he can before he has to leave the country. Discussion of Jewish religious practices. [10:00 - 20:00] Story about being invited to speak at a church in Harlem when running for City Council.Discussion of J. Raymond Jones, who later became the leader of Tammany Hall - why African Americans in Harlem were Republican and not Democrats at that time.Reflects on trip to Russia - met Sutton, O'Dwyer had just been elected on the reform ticket as President of the New York City Council. City Council years - relationship with mayor, political split of Council. [20:00 - end ] More on City Council: chain of power; financial problems when the bank did not renew the City's credit, proposal to create municipal committee headed by industry people that would have to approve budget in order for it to pass. O'Dwyer believed it took away the power from the people because the committee was not elected.Changes in New York City from when O'Dwyer first arrived to when he became President of City Council, Irish Americans' situations. (Cd 3, Track 1)
    [07:09] So, actually, the only thing they knew about their heritage and everything would have been from what the old people would have told them. But they couldn't practice it or…?
    [07:23] They held a lot back?
    [07:53] So, actually mingling in with the rest of society?
    [08:33] Was there a restriction on the age limit? You said only the older people were going to the synagogue?
    [08:40] So it was just a known thing. You were a certain age at a certain time, you could go and practice, but if you weren't, stay away?
    [09:02] So there was no underground religion at all going on there?
    [12:16 ] Do you recall who this sponsor person was?
    [12:23] What was his political affiliation at the time?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 October 1990, Oct 17, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Discusses history of New York. O'Dwyer's relationship with Jewish organizations and his work in Palestine with the American League for a Free Palestine. [10:00 - 20:00] More on work with American League for a Free Palestine; the kinds of cases his partner (Oscar Bernstien) worked on vs. his own. Receiving a medal from Ronald Reagan.More on City Hall years: experience of Vietnam, Mr. Sutton and O'Dwyer taking similar stances, often in opposition to rest of Council. [20:00 - end ] More on City Hall: O'Dwyer's opposition to bank's proposal of the municipal committee; lack of power of City Hall. History of New York and its traditions of freedom of religion and freedom of speech. (Cd 3, Track 2)
    [07:23] Do you remember the name of the organization that you were working with?
    [10:01] Was your partner, Mr. Bernstien, from your firm, also part of this?
    [11:54] Of the hundred people that were given these medals, were they mostly of Jewish extraction?
    [15:59] What years were you both in office together?
    [19:06] Why do you think that?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 24 October 1990, Oct 24, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on history of New York, tying it into the present. O'Dwyer's belief that New York gets bad press, story of him putting up a plaque celebrating New York's history in the boiler room of the AT&T building. [20:00 - end] O'Dwyer gives more details of the Horowitz case, including what was actually written about Koreh in the paper and the judge's impatience with the case. He also provides insights into libel suits, federal courts, and the importance of investigation in trials. (Cd 4, Track 1)
    [06:31] Talking about New York, and I know you have a certain fondness in your voice when you speak of New York, and you're originally from Ireland, and we all know how fond you are of Ireland. Would you say that your feelings for both countries are equal?
    Questions RE: O'Dwyer's feelings about U.S. and Ireland
    [10:00-20:00] O'Dwyer continues his answer to the question about his feelings towards the U.S. and Ireland. He speaks of how Ireland is still under tyranny and oppression and how he believes the antagonism between Protestants and Catholics in Northern Ireland is not a natural state for either side, but has been developed and fostered as a means of British supremacy.O'Dwyer explains his views on why he did not get reelected as President of the New York City Council. One of the most significant reasons being the development of the women's rights movement.The day after the election, O'Dwyer received a call from David Horowitz, who asked for help because he was being sued by a Hungarian Nazi named Koreh. Horowitz had a small newspaper that supplied news to Jewish communities in the U.S. that were not in the mainstream. Koreh sued Horowitz for libel because the paper reported that Koreh was responsible for killing 100,000 Jews in Transylvania and that he used to ride a white horse and shoot Jews.
    [25:40] Which area was that?
    [29:27] This was at the examination before trial or actually at trial?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 24 October 1990, Oct 24, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Continuing on the Horowitz case, O'Dwyer tells of the Judge's impatience with the case and how during a pre-trial conversation, the Judge ordered Horowitz to apologize for the statement about the white horse because he had no proof and to work the rest out outside of the court.O'Dwyer discusses the importance of the case for him and reveals that Koreh was later convicted for war crimes and served one year in prison in Hungary. He later lied on his application for citizenship about his conviction and became a U.S. citizen. O'Dwyer believes he could not have done this without assistance from some Washington agency.After leaving his post as the President of the City Council, O'Dwyer did not return to work for his old firm O'Dwyer and Bernstien. Instead, he worked for an Italian American organization called CIAO. He introduces another case he was involved with in which a liberal Italian organization was being taken over by another group but gets sidetracked in discussing what has happened with his old law firm. He discusses its focus on medical malpractice since he left and how his family, including his nephew Frank Durkan, and son, Brian O'Dwyer, had taken over the firm.Questions: [10:00 - 20:00] O'Dwyer explains his reasons for not returning to the firm he founded.Then he talks about his friend Charlie Keith, who started as a sailor and ended up a millionaire. He discusses their relationship, Keith's taking over O'Dwyer's campaign for City Council President, and the establishment of the Charles Keith and Carol Miller Foundation. [20:00 - 30:00] O'Dwyer finishes his discussion of Charles Keith, talking more about the foundation, its function, and his role as a trustee.Civil rights movement in Ireland and how the U.S. civil rights movement gave inspiration to the Irish; history of the antagonism between Catholics and Protestants in Northern Ireland; beginning of a story about his meeting with Something for Democracy, a civil rights organization at Queens College that helped start the movement in Northern Ireland. (Cd 4, Track 2)
    [07:27] Could he [Brian O'Dwyer] help explain to you why the doctors protected their own? Was it just a protective profession or…?
    [10:46] What year was it that you [left City Council?] …was that 1978?
    [16:05] Where was he [Charlie Keith] actually born?
    [27:12] Wouldn't you say in Ireland they've had it [British rule?] longer than anywhere else? They go back 800 - 900 years
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 November 1990, Nov 7, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] 1980 & 1981 hunger strikes in Northern Ireland by IRA and INLA prisoners attempting to regain political prisoner status; O'Dwyer's involvement in the 1981 strikes after being contacted by Hugh Logue, hunger striker Kevin Lynch's representative; advice from Attorney General Hellerman to get the hunger strikers to sign a complaint against the British government so that the European Commission on Human Rights could convene. [10:00 - 20:00] More on hunger strikes: interactions with Lynch's family and his perceptions of their attitudes toward the strike, how prisoners in Maze prison communicated with each other. Meeting with Lynch, who refused to sign the complaint. [20:00 - end] More on hunger strikes: family's reaction to Lynch's refusing to sign; O'Dwyer's meeting with members of the IRA and their distrust of O'Dwyer and the effects of the complaint; Lynch's funeral. (Cd 5, Track 1)
    [18:14] They [prisoners in Long Kesh] were allowed to go to church?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 November 1990, Nov 7, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Finishes discussion of hunger strikes: more on Lynch's funeral; continuing relationship with the Lynch family; belief that he was set up by the government; his marvel at the methods prisoners used to communicate.O'Dwyer talks about his family - his 45th wedding anniversary, his parents and the educational system in Ireland when he grew up. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Ireland's educational system: compares the training of his father and mother as teachers. Establishment of the O'Dwyer - Cheshire home for the disabled on the land where he grew up. Story of Leonard Cheshire, the World War II veteran who started the Cheshire trust. [20:00 - end] More on Cheshire, establishment of O'Dwyer - Cheshire home and how it was funded. Story of O'Dwyer's wife's, Kathleen Rohan, death and then more about the Cheshire home and how they plan to fund it in the future. (Cd 5, Track 2)
    [01:45] Why do you think they allowed ____?
    [02:34] This is done as a routine?
    [06:17] Do you think that they could have planned, members of the IRA, at the time when before their members get arrested - because they anticipate being arrested - the Irish Catholics anticipate this, this is a way of life for them in the North - that they would maybe learn how to network in the prison beforehand or know of the methods in the event that they got caught?
    [22:35] Where did the funding come from? All from the trust?
    [22:57] So the Cheshire trust name had nothing to do with Cheshire except that he established the program and then method?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 November 1990, Nov 7, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Cheshire home: how Dublin Cheshire trust was created, building of the O'Dwyer - Cheshire home, type of patients, kind of care they receive. [10:00 - end] More on O'Dwyer - Cheshire home. Surrounding village and its inhabitants, the construction of a new addition to the home and the dedication ceremony, community activities. (Cd 6, Track 1)
    [04:21] How large is the home?
    [04:32] Is that a standard for Cheshire homes?
    [06:05] What type, what actual type of people are taken in there?
    [07:49] Then are most of these people physically disabled, but not mentally disabled?
    [13:00] So that room was used then by all of these factions at any given time? It's more or less been a community center?
    [13:17] And then the residents of Cheshire house then have an activity from time to time, so it serves two great purposes?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 14 November 1990, Nov 14, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Vietnam War - how O'Dwyer became involved. The creation of a weekly lunch meeting with Phil Sipser and other like-minded people in New York area. The group's decision to oppose the reelection of Johnson in 1968. Views on Johnson's presidency - supported civil rights activities, opposed foreign policy decisions. [10:00 - 20:00] Vietnam War - discusses views of various reform groups nationwide and their inability to reach a consensus on a course of action. 1967 meeting with national liberal democratic groups in Chicago. Senator Eugene McCarthy as opponent to Johnson in election. New York caucus after the meeting. O'Dwyer's support of McCarthy, but caucus' decision not to support him. [20:00 - end] More on elections. Search for candidate to oppose Jacob Javitz for U.S. senator, formation of New Democratic Coalition, possible candidates, attempts by Robert Kennedy and Stephen Smith to stop coalition from nominating own candidate. (Cd 7, Track 1)
    [16:29] Where did you have this meeting?
    [26:09] Where was Lowenstein originally from?
    [31:50] Where did you end up having the meeting?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 14 November 1990, Nov 14, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on O'Dwyer's defense of candidate to oppose Kennedy. O'Dwyer's support of John F. Kennedy and his work as court chairman for Kennedy/Johnson ticket during their campaign. Work with Robert Kennedy. Convention in Albany when O'Dwyer was nominated as a candidate for U.S. Senator. [10:00 - 20:00] O'Dwyer's struggle to get votes, his threat to call quorum, success of his nomination. How he raised money for his campaign - funding from secular and Catholic universities. [20:00 - end] More on change in attitude of young Irish American Catholics. Election night and O'Dwyer's victory at New York primary. Refusal of regular Democratic committee to appoint McCarthy supporters their proportionate number of delegates. Bobby Kennedy's assassination. Police attacking young protestors and media outside national convention in Chicago. (Cd 7, Track 2)
    [18:51] What was the reason, do you think, for that? [ attitudes of Catholic students]
    [28:35] What were they actually protesting at that time?
    [31:56] How many young people were out there protesting? Thousands?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 16 November 1990, Nov 16, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on 1968 National Democratic Convention. Hubert Humphrey gaining more votes, McCarthy's defeat. O'Dwyer spoke at convention about his attempts at the 1964 election to nominate Eleanor Clarke French as the New York committee woman and the challenges to the committee seatings of delegates from Mississippi because they used force and intimidation to prevent minorities from voting. McKean's role in situation, O'Dwyer's defeat on the issue. [10:00 - 20:00] More on the 1968 convention. Attempts to give votes to Ted Kennedy, attempt to nominate Julian Bond for Vice President, McCarthy delegates, equipped with candles joining protestors and the peaceful conclusion of the riot. Humphrey's victory and the reasons why O'Dwyer still would not support him. [20:00 - end] More on why O'Dwyer did not support Humphrey and the reaction of the democratic community. O'Dwyer's meetings with all the democratic leaders. Humphrey's change in position about the war ten days before the election and O'Dwyer's subsequent support. (Cd 8, Track 1)
    [05:27] What was her name again?
    [07:10] This is the 196…? [1964 convention]
    [15:13] How strong were you?
    [15:20] Everyone with a candle?
    [18:19] So everything went peaceful from then on?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 16 November 1990, Nov 16, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on 1968 convention. McCarthy statement that he would support Ted Kennedy, but couldn't have supported Bobby.New York convention. Attempt by Kennedy faction to nominate James Donovan, Bobby Kennedy's offer to fly O'Dwyer and wife back to New York on his plane.Civil rights issues as O'Dwyer came into the office of the President of the City Council. [10:00 - 20:00] O'Dwyer learns of the Sullivan Principles, and used them as a jumping off point for his own proposal to prohibit the investment of New York City pension funds in any companies whose subsidiaries discriminated against minorities in Northern Ireland. Proposal delayed because Goldin (comptroller) had not approved it. Frustrations with Goldin. Eventually agreed with Goldin's caution because 11 city departments were guilty in that context. Proposal was passed by the City Council. [20:00 - end] More on MacBride Principles. Visit to a Northern Ireland airplane company where only 11% of workers were Catholic. The reaction of city stockholders to information about the 11 departments guilty of breaking McBride principles. Story of reporter who asked employer in Northern Ireland why he didn't hire Catholics. Passing of MacBride principles in City Council. Opposition to it by Dublin government at state level. (Cd 8, Track 2)
    [05:01] What did you feel at that time?
    [06:59] Is there anything in particular that went on in that plane ride?
    [12:21] Around what time is this?
    [22:55] How did Pat Darby get them? [figures about Northern Irish companies and split between Catholic vs. Protestant workers]
    [23:35] So he had a good sense of investigation. When you said before that you had to tell from the school that they came from whether they were Catholic or Protestant, so he had to do a lot of work?
    [25:05] What would that law have been? [That would have made companies break the law to conform to new rules]
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 21 November 1990, Nov 21, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer's experiences helping Irish Americans accused of working with IRA. Case of the Fort Worth Five, five Irish Americans who were charged with making false statements on their applications when buying firearms. O'Dwyer's advice to the five based on his experiences during the McCarthy Era. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Forth Worth Five. Examples of questioning during McCarthy period and how that could be used against defendants. Background on the 5th amendment. How the government undermined the 5th amendment in this case by giving them immunity and the defendants served 11 months in jail for contempt of court. [20:00 - end] More on Fort Worth Five. Appealing of case to the Supreme Court, getting bail fixed, raising money for the bail, the eventual release of the Fort Worth Five. (Cd 9, Track 1)
    [03:50] Were they all from the Texas area?
    [04:45] They were all from Manhattan then?
    [12:34] Who coined the phrase the "Fort Worth Five?"
    [22:00] It's sort of an Irish shorthand, wouldn't you say?
    [29:05] That was for each individual? [$25,000 bail]
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 21 November 1990, Nov 21, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Conclusion of Fort Worth Five discussion - protests in Texas.Brief stories of civil rights cases. Bart McKeon - man whose wife was put in jail because she would not testify against him. Desmond Macken case - IRA member convicted of shooting a soldier in the British army in Belfast. He escaped to the U.S. and sought to avoid deportation, but was extradited and convicted in a diplock court in Belfast. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Macken case. Frank Durkan, O'Dwyer's nephew, represented Macken in his attempt to deny extradition in the Manhattan federal court. History of use of political exception clause to fight extradition cases in U.S. and Britain. [20:00 - end] Another extradition case - Peter McMurray. Former IRA member and British army soldier, dissented from both organizations, Britain wanted him extradited for setting off a bomb at an army barracks near Leeds, England. (Cd 9, Track 2)
    [02:05] You mentioned that they were 11 months already that they had served in jail. That was before they got the bail?
    [22:41] When he went back he was free then?
    [31:24] Where is he living now?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 26 November 1990, Nov 26, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer and Bernstien experience with cases involving Northern Ireland and Britain. Greater intensity in cases after 1969. Change in British policy from granting convicted IRA members political status as prisoners of war to criminal status at Long Kesh prison. Protestants in Northern Ireland and O'Dwyer's contact with them on visits to Ireland. Ulster Defense Association. [10:00 - 20:00] Ulster Defense Association (UDA) and their attempts to unify the six counties of Northern Ireland into one independent state. Their lack of support for redressing discrimination in employment. O'Dwyer's meetings with Andy Terry (head of UDA). Northern Ireland Protestant history - support of democracy, philosophy of elimination of anti-Catholic laws, role in American Revolution. [20:00 - end] British internment policies, Irish American reactions to events in Ireland (British propaganda, Bloody Sunday, terrorism). American intelligence involvement in conflict and treatment of Irish Americans. Development of Brehon Law Society, an Irish American law society. (Cd 10, Track 1)
    [02:12] Which prison was this in?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 26 November 1990, Nov 26, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Brehon Laws and development of law society. Original focus on cases in which Irish Americans were accused of shipping arms back to Ireland or other similar situations. Expansion of society's focus to include countries other than Ireland. Analogy to Persian Gulf War. Description of Dublin government. Views on internment, creation of diplock court. [10:00 - 20:00] Description of diplock court. Attempt by Brehon Law Society to become non-government organization (NGO) with the United Nations. [20:00 - end] More on attempts to get NGO status. Richard Harvey and Jim Cullen's efforts. O'Dwyer's first meeting with Cullen. Attempts to establish Northern Ireland as a colony to get United Nations involved. (Cd 10, Track 2)
    [27:48] What was the year that it [Brehon Law Society] was established?
    [29:39] Are all these British colonies?